<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prashant Bhardwaj</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Prashant Bhardwaj</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>copyright@Prashant</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 22:21:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>भारत के संविधान का भाग 9 - पंचायतों के लिए नियम</title>
      <link>/hi/posts/panchayat-in-constitution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 22:21:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/hi/posts/panchayat-in-constitution/</guid>
      <description>गाँधी जी ने परिकल्पना की थी गाँवों के स्तर पर भी एक लोकतंत्र की स्थापना हो जहाँ लोग आपस में मिलजुलकर आर्थिक व् सामजिक विकास के लिए कार्य करें | साथ में इस बात की भी बकालत की थी कि ज़मीनी स्तर पर पंचायत का एक ऐसा वास्तविक लोकतंत्र खड़ा हो जिसमें प्रत्येक व्यक्ति की भागेदारी हो | जो केंद्रीय लोकतंत्र में संभव नहीं है क्योंकि वहां लोगों के द्वारा चुने हुए लोग जाते हैं लोगों की स्वयं की आवाज़ वहां नहीं पहुँचती | किन्तु प्रत्येक व्यक्ति को यह अधिकार व् अवसर मिला हुआ है कि वह अपनी ग्राम सभा की बैठक में सबके सामने अपनी बात कह सके |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>क्या किसानों को MSP पर क़ानूनी अधिकार मिलना चाहिए?</title>
      <link>/hi/posts/why-msp-not-good/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 22:07:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/hi/posts/why-msp-not-good/</guid>
      <description>बात बहुत सीधी है किसान जो अन्न उगाते हैं वो चाह रहे हैं कि कुछ ऐसा हो कि उनको अपनी उपज का अधिक से अधिक दाम मिले | और MSP की मांग करके वो ऐसा चाहते हैं कि सरकार ही एक निश्चित दाम पर उनका माल खरीदे | अब सरकार इतने अन्न को खरीदकर करेगी क्या?
अब इतने गेहूं और धान की आवश्यकता नहीं है अभी सिर्फ ६ प्रतिशत किसानों का अनाज ही MSP पर खरीदा जा रहा है और यह 6 प्रतिशत ही इतना अधिक हो जाता है कि इसको रखने का प्रबंध FCI के पास है ही नहीं | अन्नदाता के कड़ी मेहनत से उगाये अन्न का एक बड़ा हिस्सा खुले में सड़ता है, जानवर खाते हैं और अंत में FCI को आवश्यकता से अधिक अनाज आने पौने दामों में बाज़ार में बेचना पड़ता है | अब आप कहेंगे कि FCI को प्रबंध करना चाहिए अधिक भण्डारण का | लेकिन क्यों करें प्रबंध जब आवश्यकता ही नहीं है | 41.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keys to Success</title>
      <link>/posts/keys-to-success/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 22:46:54 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/keys-to-success/</guid>
      <description> Empathy Optimism Embrace ambiguity Make it Learn from failure Iterate, Iterate Creative Confidence  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jms to Kafka Bridge</title>
      <link>/posts/jms-to-kafka-bridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 23:07:49 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/jms-to-kafka-bridge/</guid>
      <description>Often we integrate two systems where one system is emitting events on some jms solution while another is listening a kafka topic and expecting source messages on kafka. In such cases, we write a bridge application which reads data from jms and writes on kafka.
This bridge application should satisfy following requirements -
 It should send messages on kafka without breaking the sequence of message. If jms broker goes down, it should keep trying to connect to that and whenever broker starts, application should reconnect and should start listening messages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Source Contributions</title>
      <link>/posts/open-source-contributions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:38:30 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/open-source-contributions/</guid>
      <description>Hugo theme - hugo-theme-hello-friend-ng  Hindi language added in langFlags and translations also added for hindi.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Stakeholders</title>
      <link>/posts/managing-stakeholders/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 14:04:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/managing-stakeholders/</guid>
      <description> Communicate Consult early and often Remember - &amp;lsquo;they are human&amp;rsquo; Plan it Relationships Show your care Manage risks Compromise Understand - what is success Take responsibilities  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Home Move - Checklist</title>
      <link>/posts/new-home-move-checklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 13:32:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/new-home-move-checklist/</guid>
      <description>A. Things to be checked with agent before you handover keys  None of your stuff left in the house, garden, sheds Bins are clear Leave some money in &amp;lsquo;Pay as you go&amp;rsquo; accounts so that when new family moves in they have things (like electricity, gas) working. If you are moving electronic applinces with you, make sure you don&amp;rsquo;t break plugs/switched and other connectors like water connectors etc. Divert your posts to your new address If you are leaving any newly purchased item in the house, don&amp;rsquo;t forget to leave guarantee/warranty papers of those items Leave smoke/fire alarms in working condition Clear all the bills (Internet, electricity, gas, water, council, factor etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Document Oriented Databases</title>
      <link>/posts/document-oriented-databases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 11:53:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/document-oriented-databases/</guid>
      <description>Overview ArangoDB CouchDB Crate.IO OrientDB SednaDB Apache-Solr RethinkDB MongoDB References  Overview A document-oriented database is a database designed for storing, retrieving and managing document-oriented information, also known as semi-structured data.
Document-oriented databases are one of the main categories of NoSQL databases, and the popularity of the term &amp;ldquo;document-oriented database&amp;rdquo; has grown with the use of the term NoSQL itself. XML databases are a subclass of document-oriented databases that are optimized to work with XML documents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>मनमर्जियां (लुटेरा - 2013)</title>
      <link>/hi/posts/manmarziyaan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 21:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/hi/posts/manmarziyaan/</guid>
      <description>यूँ तो सोलह सावन.. आये गये
गौर नहीं किया. हमने
भीगा मन का आँगन&amp;hellip; इस मर्तबा
क्या जाने क्या किया. तुमने
दिल में जागी
इश्क वाली
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां
ज़िद्द की मारी (यूँ तो सोलह)
भोली भाली (सावन)
मनमर्जियां (आये गये)
मनमर्जियां
अब तलक से
कुछ अलग सी
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां
हम ज़मीन पे (भीगा मन का)
तो फलक से (आँगन)
मनमर्जियां (इस मर्तबा)
मनमर्जियां
सिक्कों जैसे
है उछाली
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां
ज़िद्द की मारी (यूँ तो सोलह)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassandra : How is data deleted and what are Tombstones?</title>
      <link>/posts/cassandra-how-is-data-deleted-and-what-are-tombstones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 22:56:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cassandra-how-is-data-deleted-and-what-are-tombstones/</guid>
      <description>Data in Cassandra is replcated on more than one node. In another terms - &amp;lsquo;Same data is copied on more than one node&amp;rsquo;. Any change in that data should be made in all the copies of that data stored on various nodes of a cluster. Same is applied for deletes as well. If a data is deleted then it should be deleted from all the nodes. But what if any node which has a copy of that data is down.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
