<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>databases on Prashant Bhardwaj</title>
    <link>/tags/databases/</link>
    <description>Recent content in databases on Prashant Bhardwaj</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>copyright@Prashant</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 11:53:57 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/databases/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Document Oriented Databases</title>
      <link>/posts/document-oriented-databases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 11:53:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/document-oriented-databases/</guid>
      <description>Overview ArangoDB CouchDB Crate.IO OrientDB SednaDB Apache-Solr RethinkDB MongoDB References  Overview A document-oriented database is a database designed for storing, retrieving and managing document-oriented information, also known as semi-structured data.
Document-oriented databases are one of the main categories of NoSQL databases, and the popularity of the term &amp;ldquo;document-oriented database&amp;rdquo; has grown with the use of the term NoSQL itself. XML databases are a subclass of document-oriented databases that are optimized to work with XML documents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassandra : How is data deleted and what are Tombstones?</title>
      <link>/posts/cassandra-how-is-data-deleted-and-what-are-tombstones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 22:56:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cassandra-how-is-data-deleted-and-what-are-tombstones/</guid>
      <description>Data in Cassandra is replcated on more than one node. In another terms - &amp;lsquo;Same data is copied on more than one node&amp;rsquo;. Any change in that data should be made in all the copies of that data stored on various nodes of a cluster. Same is applied for deletes as well. If a data is deleted then it should be deleted from all the nodes. But what if any node which has a copy of that data is down.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassandra : Replication Strategies</title>
      <link>/posts/cassandra-replication-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2019 13:49:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cassandra-replication-strategies/</guid>
      <description>There are two kinds of replication strategies in Cassandra.
SimpleStrategy is used when you have just one data center. SimpleStrategy places the first replica on the node selected by the partitioner. After that, remaining replicas are placed in clockwise direction in the Node ring.
NetworkTopologyStrategy is used when you have more than two data centers.
In NetworkTopologyStrategy, replicas are set for each data center separately. NetworkTopologyStrategy places replicas in the clockwise direction in the ring until reaches the first node in another rack.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassandra : Consistency Levels List</title>
      <link>/posts/cassandra-consistency-levels-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 11:19:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cassandra-consistency-levels-list/</guid>
      <description>Typical values of consistency levels are -
Note - Write operation consists of writing to commit log and memtable.
   Level Write Read Usage     ALL A write must be on all replica nodes in the cluster for that partition. Returns the record after all replicas. The read operation will fail if a replica does not respond. Provides the highest consistency and the lowest availability of any other level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassandra : Replication Factor &amp; Consistency Level</title>
      <link>/posts/cassandra-replication-factor-consistency-level/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 09:31:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cassandra-replication-factor-consistency-level/</guid>
      <description>In a production system, it is advisable to have three or more Cassandra nodes in each data center, and the default replication factor should be three. As a general rule, the replication factor should not exceed the number of Cassandra nodes in the cluster. If there are 3 nodes in your cluster then how can you store data on more than three nodes?
If you add additional Cassandra nodes to the cluster, the default replication factor is not affected.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassandra : When not to use</title>
      <link>/posts/cassandra-when-not-to-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 23:36:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cassandra-when-not-to-use/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t think that I need to explain what Cassandra is. OK, one liner is enough ! It is NoSQL database, primarily used in big data projects.
Before we start discussing scenarios where Cassandra fits very well, let&amp;rsquo;s discuss where it doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit at all.
We&amp;rsquo;ll have lots of data, let&amp;rsquo;s use Cassandra
Cassandra is not a typical database which fits in every Big Data use case. In some no big data cases also it can fit very well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cassandra : Overview, how is data written and read?</title>
      <link>/posts/cassandra-overview-how-is-data-written-and-read/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 17:01:38 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cassandra-overview-how-is-data-written-and-read/</guid>
      <description>[Characterstics] (#h2-characterstics-h2) [How does it internally work] (#h2-how-does-it-internally-work-h2) [References] (#h2-references-h2)  The Apache Cassandra database is the right choice when you need scalability and high availability without compromising performance. Linear scalability and proven fault-tolerance on commodity hardware or cloud infrastructure make it the perfect platform for mission-critical data. Cassandra&amp;rsquo;s support for replicating across multiple datacenters is best-in-class, providing lower latency for your users and the peace of mind of knowing that you can survive regional outages.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
