<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on प्रशान्त भारद्वाज</title>
        <link>/hi/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on प्रशान्त भारद्वाज</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>copyright@Prashant</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 21:11:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="/hi/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>मनमर्जियां (लुटेरा - 2013)</title>
            <link>/hi/posts/2019/11/%E0%A4%AE%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%AE%E0%A4%B0%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%9C%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%82-%E0%A4%B2%E0%A5%81%E0%A4%9F%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE-2013/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 21:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/hi/posts/2019/11/%E0%A4%AE%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%AE%E0%A4%B0%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%9C%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%82-%E0%A4%B2%E0%A5%81%E0%A4%9F%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE-2013/</guid>
            <description>यूँ तो सोलह सावन.. आये गये
गौर नहीं किया. हमने
भीगा मन का आँगन&amp;hellip; इस मर्तबा
क्या जाने क्या किया. तुमने
दिल में जागी
इश्क वाली
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां
ज़िद्द की मारी (यूँ तो सोलह)
भोली भाली (सावन)
मनमर्जियां (आये गये)
मनमर्जियां
अब तलक से
कुछ अलग सी
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां
हम ज़मीन पे (भीगा मन का)
तो फलक से (आँगन)
मनमर्जियां (इस मर्तबा)
मनमर्जियां
सिक्कों जैसे
है उछाली
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां
ज़िद्द की मारी (यूँ तो सोलह)</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>यूँ तो सोलह सावन.. आये गये<br />
गौर नहीं किया. हमने<br />
भीगा मन का आँगन&hellip; इस मर्तबा<br />
क्या जाने क्या किया. तुमने</p>

<p>दिल में जागी<br />
इश्क वाली<br />
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां</p>

<p>ज़िद्द की मारी (यूँ तो सोलह)<br />
भोली भाली (सावन)<br />
मनमर्जियां (आये गये)<br />
मनमर्जियां</p>

<p>अब तलक से<br />
कुछ अलग सी<br />
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां<br />
हम ज़मीन पे (भीगा मन का)<br />
तो फलक से (आँगन)<br />
मनमर्जियां (इस मर्तबा)<br />
मनमर्जियां</p>

<p>सिक्कों जैसे<br />
है उछाली<br />
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां<br />
ज़िद्द की मारी (यूँ तो सोलह)<br />
भोली भाली (सावन)<br />
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां (आये गये)</p>

<p>बे-अदब सी<br />
पर गज़ब सी<br />
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां</p>

<p>होश खोया<br />
पर संभाली मनमर्जियां (यूँ तो सोलह)<br />
मनमर्जियां (सावन)<br />
ज़िद्द की मारी (आये गये)<br />
भोली भाली<br />
मनमर्जियां, मनमर्जियां</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>प्रत्येक व्यक्ति का कल्याण कैसे संभव?</title>
            <link>/hi/posts/2019/08/%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%A4%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%95-%E0%A4%B5%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4%E0%A4%BF-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%BE-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%B2%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A3-%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%88%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%87-%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%82%E0%A4%AD%E0%A4%B5/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 23:10:51 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/hi/posts/2019/08/%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%A4%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%95-%E0%A4%B5%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4%E0%A4%BF-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%BE-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%B2%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A3-%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%88%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%87-%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%82%E0%A4%AD%E0%A4%B5/</guid>
            <description>कल्याण की कामना कौन नहीं रखता, प्रत्येक व्यक्ति रखता है और व्यक्ति अपने और अपने परिवार के कल्याण हेतु सर्वदा हर सम्भव प्रयास करता रहता है ! किन्तु विरले मनुष्य यह जानते हैं कि हम सबके कल्याण में एक दूसरे का कल्याण छुपा है। हम सब मोतियों की माला हैं अगर एक भी मोती टूटा तो पूरी माला की रौनक बिगड़ जाती है।
छोटे छोटे मूंगों की माला में यदि एक सेर भर का मोती लगा दिया तो क्या होगा?</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>कल्याण की कामना कौन नहीं रखता, प्रत्येक व्यक्ति रखता है और व्यक्ति अपने और अपने परिवार के कल्याण हेतु सर्वदा हर सम्भव प्रयास करता रहता है ! किन्तु विरले मनुष्य यह जानते हैं कि हम सबके कल्याण में एक दूसरे का कल्याण छुपा है। हम सब मोतियों की माला हैं अगर एक भी मोती टूटा तो पूरी माला की रौनक बिगड़ जाती है।</p>

<p>छोटे छोटे मूंगों की माला में यदि एक सेर भर का मोती लगा दिया तो क्या होगा? वो माला तब तक ही सुरक्षित रहेगी जब तक उस भारी मोती को पकड़कर उसे उठाया जाएगा, जैसे ही किसी अन्य मूंगे की ओर से पकड़कर यदि माला उठाई तो भारी मोती के भार से माला टूट जायेगी | इस बात को कहने का अर्थ मात्र इतना सा ही है कि समाज में अगर कोई एक अत्यंत ही शक्तिशाली व्यक्ति या परिवार आ जाये तो समाज तब तक ही सुरक्षित है जब तक वह शक्ति समाज का भार उठाये यदि वह शक्ति है यह मान बैठे की समाज उसका भार उठाएगा तब तो समाज का बिघटन सुनिश्चित है !</p>

<p>आदि काल से लेकर और आज से लगभग २०० वर्ष पहले तक भी मनुष्य के क्रियाकलाप की सीमा उसकी सीमा तक ही थी ! जैसे आवागमन के लिए घोड़े का प्रयोग किया जाता था जिसकी गति मनुष्य की गति से बहुत अधिक नहीं होती! कहने का अभिप्राय यह है कि कार, रेलगाड़ी इत्यादि मनुष्य की सीमाओं से परे हैं !</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Hugo का प्रयोग कर बनायें अपनी वेबसाइट, करें होस्ट GitHub Pages पर वो भी मुफ़्त में  </title>
            <link>/hi/posts/2019/08/hugo-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%BE-%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%AF%E0%A5%8B%E0%A4%97-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%B0-%E0%A4%AC%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%AF%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%82-%E0%A4%85%E0%A4%AA%E0%A4%A8%E0%A5%80-%E0%A4%B5%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%AC%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%87%E0%A4%9F-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%B0%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%82-%E0%A4%B9%E0%A5%8B%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%9F-github-pages-%E0%A4%AA%E0%A4%B0-%E0%A4%B5%E0%A5%8B-%E0%A4%AD%E0%A5%80-%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%81%E0%A5%9E%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4-%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%82/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 23:22:50 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/hi/posts/2019/08/hugo-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%BE-%E0%A4%AA%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%AF%E0%A5%8B%E0%A4%97-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%B0-%E0%A4%AC%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%AF%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%82-%E0%A4%85%E0%A4%AA%E0%A4%A8%E0%A5%80-%E0%A4%B5%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%AC%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%87%E0%A4%9F-%E0%A4%95%E0%A4%B0%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%82-%E0%A4%B9%E0%A5%8B%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%9F-github-pages-%E0%A4%AA%E0%A4%B0-%E0%A4%B5%E0%A5%8B-%E0%A4%AD%E0%A5%80-%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%81%E0%A5%9E%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4-%E0%A4%AE%E0%A5%87%E0%A4%82/</guid>
            <description>Overview GitHub came up with GitHub pages service, which hosts static web content free of cost. For Tech bloggers and for those who are trying to make their hands dirty in static web content creation, this is the best service at this moment. Read tagline of GitHub Pages -
GoHugo is one of the most popular open-source static site generators. With its amazing speed and flexibility, GoHugo makes building websites fun again.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>

<p><strong>GitHub</strong> came up with <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub pages service</a>, which hosts static web content free of cost. For Tech bloggers and for those who are trying to make their hands dirty in static web content creation, this is the best service at this moment. Read tagline of GitHub Pages -</p>

<p><img src="/GitHub-pages-intro.PNG" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p><strong>GoHugo</strong> is one of the most popular open-source <a href="https://gohugo.io/">static site generators</a>. With its amazing speed and flexibility, GoHugo makes building websites fun again. It is <a href="https://themes.gohugo.io/">theme</a> based framework. You write markdown files and hugo creates static html by blending the content written in markdown files with the theme you selected. I am using <a href="https://themes.gohugo.io/hugo-theme-hello-friend-ng/">hello-friend-ng</a> theme for this website. And this entire post is written in single markdown file. Result is in-front of you. In future, I can choose any other theme and same content then will be presented differently on UI.</p>

<p><img src="/Hugo-intro.PNG" alt="alt text" /></p>

<p>Now, In this post I will explain the step by step procedure to create a personal blog site using Hugo and then hosting this on GitHubPages.</p>

<h3 id="step-1-repository-setup-in-github">Step 1 - Repository setup in GitHub</h3>

<h4 id="1-1-to-create-a-user-page-site-on-github-pages-create-a-repository-using-the-naming-scheme-lt-username-gt-github-io">1.1 - To create a User Page site on GitHub Pages, create a repository using the naming scheme  &lt;username&gt;.github.io.</h4>

<p>My GitHub username is prashantbhardwaj hence I created a repository with the name as <em>prashantbhardwaj.github.io</em>.
Now, when I will push any static web contents like HTML, CSS or JS files, those files will be hosted on GitHub Pages and can be accessed on this <a href="https://prashantbhardwaj.github.io">URL</a>. Please Note - Content from the master branch will be used to publish your GitHub Pages site.</p>

<h4 id="1-2-now-create-one-more-repository-to-keep-the-code-of-your-hugo-website-project">1.2 - Now create one more repository to keep the code of your Hugo Website project.</h4>

<p>GoHugo will be used to create static content of your website. To do so, you need a github repository to keep you Hugo project code. Finally that generated static content will be pushed into &lt;username&gt;.github.io repository. You can give any name for your GoHugo project repository. I chose <em>website</em>.</p>

<h4 id="please-note">Please note</h4>

<p>These two repository will remain blank until step 3. Later we will use these repositories to push static website content and the GoHugo code which will be used to generate these static web content.</p>

<h3 id="step-2-gohugo-installation">Step 2 - GoHugo installation</h3>

<p>To install GoHugo in your local machine, follow steps mentioned on this <a href="https://gohugo.io/getting-started/installing/">page</a>.</p>

<h3 id="step-3-learn-gohugo">Step 3 - Learn GoHugo</h3>

<p>Check this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qtIqKaDlqXo&amp;list=PLLAZ4kZ9dFpOnyRlyS-liKL5ReHDcj4G3">YouTube playlist</a>, to learn GoHugo, step by step. During this learning exercise you will also create your GoHugo website project.</p>

<h3 id="step-4-link-your-gohugo-project-to-your-github-repository">Step 4 - Link your GoHugo project to your github repository.</h3>

<p>I hope during learning GoHugo by watching the youtube clips mentioned in previous step, you created your project. Now, it is time to link your GoHugo project with your website project repository you created under step 1.2. Steps to link your project code with GitHub repository are mentioned on your GitHub repository home page. Open that home page on your GitHub repository website and follow them.</p>

<h3 id="step-5-link-your-theme-subproject-with-its-github-repository">Step 5 - Link your theme subproject with its github repository.</h3>

<p>I hope during learning GoHugo by watching the youtube clips mentioned in previous step, you created your project and if so then probably you downloaded your chosen theme from it&rsquo;s GitHub repository. For my project, I cloned hello-friend-ng theme from <a href="https://github.com/rhazdon/hugo-theme-hello-friend-ng.git">it&rsquo;s github repository</a> in my project&rsquo;s themes directory. As mentioned on <a href="https://themes.gohugo.io/hugo-theme-hello-friend-ng/">hello-friend-ng</a> website, I used following command to link this theme subproject with my main website project -</p>

<p><code>$ git submodule add https://github.com/rhazdon/hugo-theme-hello-friend-ng.git themes/hello-friend-ng</code></p>

<p>There is a benefit of linking your theme subproject with your theme&rsquo;s GitHub repository - whenever there will be any changes in your theme&rsquo;s code, you can very easily download them by using <code>git clone</code> command.</p>

<h3 id="step-6-generate-static-content-of-your-website">Step 6 - Generate static content of your website</h3>

<p><code>hugo -t theme-name</code> command generates static content of your website in <code>/public</code> directory. If you will link this directory with the repository created under step 1.1 the by just pushing that generated static web content, your website will be hosted on GitHubPages. Steps to link your <code>/public</code> with GitHub repository are mentioned on your GitHub repository home page. Open that home page on your GitHub repository website and follow them.</p>

<p>Now add this github project as submodule with your main website project. Detailed steps are mentioned <a href="https://gohugo.io/hosting-and-deployment/hosting-on-github/">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="useful-links">Useful Links</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qtIqKaDlqXo&amp;list=PLLAZ4kZ9dFpOnyRlyS-liKL5ReHDcj4G3">Videos to learn GoHugo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet#emphasis">Markdown cheatsheet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://gohugo.io/getting-started/installing/">GoHugo Installation steps</a></li>
<li><a href="https://gohugo.io/hosting-and-deployment/hosting-on-github/">GoHost Hugo site on GitHub</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
